hello and welcome to the 29th tutorial
on how to program in gript 2 so in the
last few tutorials I've been explaining
how to use class scripts and things like
that well in this tutorial I want to
finish teaching classes and how to use
them okay so let's make a mining script
in this tutorial first let's go to
classes and create a new class and call
it gem okay then here let's just put
something simple for testing function on
created set
image what do I want green rupe so it
looks like a gem PNG this is an image I
have by the way it might not work for
you so you want to use something
else then to delete it function
on player touches
me then let's put this do
destroy okay let's apply this
now let's minimize this and open our
level editor you can ignore these two
NPCs right here so let's put down a new
MPC and add some
code what do we
want client side function
oncreated for an image we're going to
put set image orbital Rock another image
that I
have and here function on was
hit okay this is important now we're
going to
put a command called Trigger action now
I've explained this in the past but I've
never been able to show an actual
playable example now what Trigger action
does what Trigger action is
is
and is trigger server for level NPCs now
trigger server trigger server will not
work for level NPCs and I'm not sure why
I think it has to do something with
level NPCs technically not having an ID
so the server can't reach them or
something like that so we have to put
Tri Trigger
action now the first parameter we're
going to put this.x second
this.y now this is the location of the
actual action and we want it to be on
the NPC I'm not sure what changing is
even does putting them to zero and zero
makes it not even work and the only way
I've been able to make it even be used
is to put this.x and this.y or just X
and Y and that just it just
automatically gets it okay anyway let's
put some quotes here and then put n
because we don't want to send any
variables over now over here on server
side we're going to put function on
action and leave it like that for
now okay so over here in the quotes the
third parameter of trigger Trigger
action is pretty important this
specifies which trigger I mean which fun
what what which onaction function we
want to go to so if we put something
like make gem and over here on function
on action we put make gem then this
Trigger action would know to go to this
function over here now if we change this
to maybe put gem instead of make gem it
would go hey where is make gem I only
see put Gem and it won't even work so we
need to make these equal let's just
replace this
with put gem okay so here's our function
in the function we're going to put put
npc2 and drop down the class as an NPC
which I've showed you
previously X well we want to put this.x
this.y this is where the NPC is going to
go and then all this all these crazy
letters and
symbols is that
right possibly okay so here's our here's
the name of our class that we're going
to put down as an NPC let's close
this now oh we don't want
that let's clear the level
first
there now I'm going to save it
again now I'm going to hit
it oh why isn't anything happening well
there's a reason for that if we go to
our level
editor and we go here we can see
everything looks right Trigger action
and put npc2 well here's a problem with
triger action you can't use it unless
you specify the set shape of the um NPC
on server side so let's just do that
function on created so as soon as the
NPC is created it's going to have a set
shape set shape 1 comma 32 comma 32 now
don't ask why you need this to use
Trigger action but you need to have set
shape somewhere in server side before
you are able to use Trigger action
so now that we got that let's save it
again and hit it nothing's happening
again let's clear the NPCs one more
time
nope here's our
class here is our
NPC
um it's probably something really simple
that I I'm totally
missing okay I think I figured it out
when I open this I'm putting
the uh class onto the
NPC which is blocking it so if I put
something like Plus one for the X I'll
be able to see it
now wasn't really a programming eror
just I couldn't see the image
anyway as you can see there's some of
the image let me just change that a bit
and make it a bit more so there this is
xals
okay I hit it there it is and if I hit
the uh rupe it'll be
destroyed okay well we have that now
let's open our NPC again and put hide so
it hides The Rock once the and you can't
even use the rock anymore once the uh
NPC is placed okay let's save that one
more time and
upload there there's the rupe and we can
hit it it'll disappear now let's open
our class
again let's delete this function
here and add a client side client side
then let's put function no no
functions yeah yes function function on
created and then
put we'll just leave that for now then
over here we're going to put function
on player touches
me and we're going to make it so that if
a player touches it on client side it's
going to be destroyed so let's put
something uh
if we're going to put trigger server and
instead ofgi we're going to put NPC
since this is technically an NPC then
we're going to put uh what we want to
destroy this. name then
null up here we're going to put function
on action server
side I'm going to put this dot destroy
so seeing this right now actually I'm
going to take out the on created since
it's taking up room so when you look at
this it should work right on client side
if any player touches it it's going to
go to server side and Destroy for
everyone well that's actually not the
case this will not work and I'll show
you right
now let me just upload a level again I
create this hery and I hit it and hey
it's not working well there's a reason
for that If This Were instead of client
side on server side then it would
actually work well if this destroy was
under uh on play touches me but since
under client side it's not working and
there's a reason for that for some
reason classes if you try to try to use
try to destroy them by using trigger
server I mean using trigger server it's
not going to work this.name it doesn't
know what this.name is of course we know
we're trying to specify the this current
class but it doesn't know well to
counter that over here on oncreated
we're going to put
this.at
attribute and in the attribute we're
going to put a number three so it's in
Array really then we're going to put
this.name then down here instead of
this.name going to put this. ATR at then
two now ATR is like a special array or
whatever that has these variables and
they apparently can get held for
different classes I'm not very sure but
whatever the case you have to have this
on oncreated on server side to be able
to
call uh this exact NPC and make it be
destroyed okay let's reply
that and let's clear the
area next let's update the level again
and it's I touched it and it disappeared
so we know it's
working so we have some uh of our mining
script done but there's more we can do
let's open our level editor again and
here right before put NPC 2 we're going
to put temp.
obj equals I'll space it out so it's
easier to
read then over here we're going to put
temp do actually I'm going to explain
that first first what we're doing is
we're making the
NPC that we just placed down as a class
equal to this temp
variable now if we take this and put
temp. obj which is the NPC that we just
Place input
a and some a number other than two since
we're already using that we can put
equals whatever variable we want since
we can put um
hello or something like that well let's
put something more practical like let's
put the player. account so the player
that just hit the
rock and placed the NPC down we're going
to have a variable in that specific NPC
equal to the player's account name and
I'll see you show you what that does in
a second let's close this save it and
over here in the NPC let's put function
on
created and then put under client side
and put this. chat is equal to ATR and
three I mean this do ATR that I put this
dot here oh doesn't need there but here
you need it
apparently
okay let's upload
it I'm going to hit it and just it's
saying my account
that's great so we can take it now and
that's good but for our mining script we
can see that this player right
here we're going to update the level if
they hit
it and drop down the uh oh I'm making
the rock hide on client side I should
change that they're making the class
appear with their uh account on it but I
can still take it well let's change that
first let's go into levelator and make
it so it hides on server side let's put
that here on server side okay that's
good then we're going to hide that we
going to test
it yeah it works okay now here in the
class let's put something useful for
this variable we have here that is
holding the player's account we can
put this do no let's not put that yet
let's
put over
here if player. account so if the
player's touching it if their account is
equal to this do a
ATR so if it's equal to the account then
that pressed it
earlier then we're going to drop
it I'm back now where was I oh yeah if
player. account is equal to the account
of the player who first made the NPC
appear then we're going to have this
happen Okay let's apply
that
then we're going to upload this
again now if I hit it and select the
other
player well who's in trial right now so
I'll show you in a second but I can take
it but now if I update the
level hit it it has my account now on it
but but if I let the other player take
it he's not going to be able to which
I'll show you in a second with the trial
Observer mode is out one
second okay I'm back now
look as you can see I'm moving around
this test account right now and if he
tries to take it he's not going to be
able to because his count isn't equal to
AT3 which is the account that was set
when I hit the rock here but if I try to
take it it will work now in terms of a
mining
script this is pretty good but let's say
the player goes off line now it's going
to have a um rupee right here that no
one be able to take because it's going
to have my account on it and no one can
take it well let's just straighten that
out right here let's go here and on Crea
let's put this dot timer equals whatever
you want 20 then we're going to put on
timeout here we're going to put function
on
timeout
here we're going to put set timer which
is going to take one
second um here let's put this
dot timer minus minus so it's going to
subtract one every second then here
let's copy this chat and here is it's
looping it's going to say our account
then at
sign some
a dash or minus sign then another at
sign to split up the variables and
strings and we're going to
put the time this do timer so it's SPL
it's saying all the things at once and
those things are being split up between
these at
signs and I'll show you what that looks
like I'm going to apply
this I'll update the
level now if I hit this you can see it
says 18 17 16 15 it's going to go all
the way to well negative
Infinity let's just change
that
if um if this do timer is greater than
zero then it's going to go
down now once it reaches zero we want
everyone to be able to take it so over
here where it says if play. account is
equal to you know the account then it's
going to be able to be deleted we're
going to put an or and then or
this.timer is less than or equal to zero
so once the timer is zero then anyone
would be able to take
it and over
here let's put another
statement we're going to take this copy
this text first and put it over here so
if the timer is greater than zero then
it's going to do all this but else so if
the timer is less than or equal to zero
then this. chat is equal to free to take
also just for testing let's lower the
limit to
uh 6
seconds okay let's update that save the
NPC now let's do this I hit the rock and
it creates a
NPC it's going to go to
zero then it's going to say free to take
and anyone will be able to take it so
even though I was the one that hit the
rock and placed the NPC this test player
is going to be able to take it now let's
try this again before it reaches
zero oh I hit the rock now as the player
I can't take it
see but once it's zero I can't take it
which is great if you're doing a mining
script if you were doing a Min script
you want want it to add up so you would
want to put player. client. gems is
equal to whatever plus one but we're not
going to do that anyway I guess this
tutorial is over I hope you understand
how to place NPCs better how to send
over variables to NPCs as you can see
here in the uh level NPC I'm setting o
I'm I'm making attribute 3 equal to
whatever variable I want and then using
those in the actual uh
NPC also I explain how to delete them if
you're going
from client side in the class and I also
showed you how to use trigger server in
classes anyway that concludes the
tutorial and I want to show you one more
thing before I go so let's go to this
level
editor over here and let's make it
um
sleep five then put show again so it's
going to sleep for 5 seconds then what
show appears again it you'll be able to
hit the rock again and create more uh
rupes and
gems let's save
that so we wait for it to reach zero or
5 seconds and appears again I can hit it
and there are two now there but I'll
just take
both and now if we go to level Eder we
can copy paste the script a bunch of
times and we have a bunch of rocks that
will
place these gems which you can
take and that's a pretty basic mining
script if you wanted to you could add
animations like a gani or if you
pronounce it Gan like that so there's
like a pickaxe and maybe I have health
through the Rocks but that's another
day I hope you enjoyed this tutorial and
I will see you next time